Okay, we're gonna go to the Lamrim ...
I've been teaching it for ... I don't know ... eight years. I promised to finish this book, it's
very long, it's about a thousand pages,
and ... I think it's the greatest book ever
written, and it's a ... Lamrim means Steps
of the Path to Buddhahood, for dummies.
Lam .. Buddhahood for dummies okay,
and ... you just do these things and you get
to enlightenment, you don't have to think
about it okay? So, it's just a list of
things that you have to do, and by the end you become enlightened okay?
So, that's called Lamrim. Who can tell
me how Lamrim relates to the five
topics and the four schools we had
yesterday? Who wants to take a shot? How
does the Geshe course relate to Lamrim?
Pyotr Velikiy.
Yeah five topics
Cool! Very good. Ok, so ... if you have time, and if you're very
passionate, you do the Geshe course okay? If you have time and you're very
passionate you do the Geshe course,
it's deeper okay?
It's deep deep, if you don't have time, if
you're a farmer in Tibet, then you just ...
maybe once a month, every two months, you go to a day with a Lama and
you do Lamrim. So, Lamrim is kinda ... that's the relationship. Lamrim has all the
basic information that's in the Geshe
course, but not as detailed, which you're
going to see today and tomorrow okay, not as detailed, but it's a good solid summary
of all of Buddhism okay, so I took people
through the Geshe course, first turning
of the wheel, I did the Vajrayana course,
Diamond Way course, second turning the
wheel, third turning of the wheel is okay let's do the whole thing in a ... in a way that
you can use it in your ACI teaching okay,
like if you have students who can't
do the whole Geshe course okay, if they
don't have time, then do a Lamrim with
them okay? Now, trick question for zero
dollars. They got in a bad habit of
demanding money for answers, especially
somebody. What would be a great short
Lamrim that you could teach people?
Yeah, the Three Principal Paths, which is
the first ACI course, okay got it?
Why would a baby teacher start with that
text in the 18 courses? Well, in case the
student quits.
They got the whole Lamrim in the
first course okay, so alright? So, that's
not a bad strategy okay, alright. So ...
we're doing two Lamrims this week, you
see what I mean? In the evening, you're
learning how to teach the shortest Lamrim in history, 14 verses okay?
Say, Lam tso nam sum, the three main
teachings of Buddhism okay, that's all.
It's the shortest Lamrim there is,
roughly okay, and then in the morning
you're doing the longest Lamrim there
is, one of the longest Lamrims, okay ... so
we're doing the great Lamrim of
Pabongkha Rinpoche
alright, who wrote the commentary for
this evening's Lamrim? Pabongkha Rinpoche okay?
it's the same person okay, you're ... in
the morning you're studying his
thousand-page book, and in the evening
you're studying his two page book, got it?
Okay, and you know, I was having lunch
with some people I remember it was my
old lady, Mrs. Hancock and her boyfriend
who ditched her, but anyway she's 93 ... and
we were like ... what's the ... what's your
favorite book of all time? And you know
somebody said Gone with the Wind, I said ah, Lamrim Namdrul Lakchang, you know A Gift of
Liberation Thrust Into Your Hands ...
and I think it's the greatest book ever
written, I think it's the greatest book
on this planet okay, so we're going
through it, what do you call it,
savoring it okay? Savor means, "enjoy the
taste slowly", and don't rush
okay, so we're savoring this Lamrim and
it's going to take about ... the whole thing
will take about 15 years ... we're about
halfway through okay, and ... I promised you
dessert. If you don't remember, this Lamrim,
which is one of the longest in
history, doesn't have a huge section on
shamantha and vipashyana okay, it's not
"vipassana" okay, I don't know who did
that ... I'm always suspicious of things
when they misspelled the name of the
leader, or like Sivananda ... anyway
the final section of the Lamrim is how to
develop the meditation which sees
kong xing, emptiness directly okay,
the final section of the Lamrim is
always that. Pabongkha Rinpoche decided not to focus on it, he didn't make it huge,
why? Je Tsongkapa already did it, his ... Je Tsongkapa's Lamrim Chenmo has about ... I
don't know 300 pages on that, and so I
promised you for dessert that, which
would take another eight years or
something okay, so ... we're here for a while.
Annie's going to be a an old lady by the time we finish okay?
I'm gonna be ... I don't know okay ... alright?
So, that's our plan, that's our strategy,
we're in the middle somewhere,
we're just about halfway through okay,
here we go ...
Text, text back. I'm putting the text up
just for you to follow okay,
it's a good seed for you guys
in case you want to be a translator, we
have Judy right? She's here, where are you?
Ya, no ... Joy, there! She's helping run the
translation team in China, we have ... I
don't know how many, 40? 40 translators
there okay, we have about 20 in Sedona
okay, anyway ... so it's just to put seeds in
your mind okay, but I'm gonna go word for
word, and I'm gonna enjoy the taste very
slow okay, and I don't care if you're
bored, or you don't want to study Tibetan
because I'm putting a seed in your mind,
next life we'll ... you'll be on Joy's
translation team okay? Alright, here we
go, RNAM 'GREL LAS KYANG, he's quoting
namdrel (RNAM 'GREL), what's namdrel? wait ... which topic? Which topic? Yeah, clear thinking,
which number? Three okay, topic number
three, he's quoting the mother book of
all clear thinking, which is by?
Chandrakirti ...ah the other kirti okay,
Dharmakirti okay ...
and it says ,SRID PA'I SRED LAS RNAM BRGAL BA'I,
,LAS GZHAN 'PHEN NUS MA YIN TE,
,LHAN CIG BYED PA ZAD PHYIR RO,
okay very famous. Now, Wheel of Life, 12 links,
two of them are karma, which one's?
Number? 2 and 10 yeah,
God, other people a chance man ... okay,
what's the difference between 2 and 10,
okay, there's 2 ... 2 of the 12
links are karma, you're committing karma,
okay, the first one is the second link,
what's the picture?
Somebody's making pots okay, which means
you're making karmic seeds
the pots are karmic seeds okay, so in
the Wheel of Life picture the guy is
making pots, it means his karma, but it's
what kind of karma? Fresh, okay, so right
now in the last few
months in ... I have a garden and it's time
to plant things okay, we just planted
bulbs and watermelons okay, so when you
first put the seed in the ground that's
called fresh karma okay,
duje kyi le, sanskara in sanskrit
okay, sanskara, then it cooks, and cooks,
and cooks okay, it gets water, it gets
sunlight, it gets warmth, it gets fertilizer,
and then link number? 10, which is a?
Pregnant lady ... the seed is reached ... I
don't know
August? You see? Number two is the seed in
March, and number ten is the seed in
August, and there's been lots of rain, and
sunlight, and fertilizer, I get this thing
okay, it's very clear in my mind, it's
hard to explain. When you put the seed in
the ground all the dudes inside are
asleep, there's a whole staff, factory
staff, sitting inside the seed and
they're all like sleepy okay, then you
put water on the seed, which is actually
impossible, water touches the seed and
then ... they wake up, and I see this like ...
it's like October in the jewelry,
business what's that mean? Can you turn
it up a little [mic], huh? Yeah Christmas is coming,
sixty percent of diamonds are sold in
one week, so in October everyone's like ahhh ... everyone's going crazy, so i see it in
the seed, inside the seed, all the workers
are like ah we gotta get this
watermelon out you know, and they ... this is not too loud enough something's wrong [mic] ...
yeah ... they all go crazy okay, and then
number ten in August the seed is ready
to split open, the seed is pregnant, the
the baby's about to come okay? Now, this
lamrim right here,
third school, third topic, interesting
okay, second school right?
They are suddenly talking about what
makes to two go to ten okay, for a tree seed,
for a watermelon seed it's what? Sunlight,
water, fertilizer, right? But what is it in
your mind that makes the seed go from
two to ten? Coffee meditation, great! For ...
good seeds, for bad seeds? Now, listen okay,
this is deep okay,
if you plant good seeds in your mind and
you want them to grow and get pregnant
and have a big baby,
like Katie just had, then do lots of
rejoicing okay, before you go to bed
think about all the good things you did
and and they will get fatter and fatter.
That wakes up the factory, rejoicing
wakes up the factory in a good seed, okay
got it?
But what wakes up the factory in a bad
seed? Word say it nice ... it's a very
interesting answer, what's the opposite
of coffee meditation? Yeah, yeah, listen, the
way to get a bad seed pregnant is to not
understand it ... cool? It's very interesting
okay,
the way to make bad seeds grow fatter and
faster is just to not understand how
they work, okay cool? It's the
opposite of rejoicing okay, you would
think rejoicing, the opposite would be
anger or something, it's not. It's just
misunderstanding the seeds. Is there any
misunderstanding in rejoicing? Yeah, and
that's what we call dirty good karma,
dirty good karma, okay the karma for Ben
and Jerry's
Cherry Garcia, which is dear to my heart
okay?
Is it a good kind of bad karma or bad karma?
I mean it's a good karma, in my three-year
retreat I ate a whole bucket of it one
day for my birthday,
it was the only ice cream I had for
three years, I threw up. Okay,
so, but is there a bad part of the ice
cream? Yeah, it runs out okay, so that's
the bad part, that's a bad seed okay?
What made the ice cream run out is that
I didn't understand ice cream okay, like
I wanted it, but I didn't understand it,
you see? If I really understood it I
would have sent half of it back to Jigme
for the caretakers to enjoy, understand?
Then I'd make more, but my desire took over.
Yes Steven? Loud .... oh yeah we'll get there
let's talk about it, what is it about
misunderstanding that makes the seed get
fatter? Okay, we'll talk about it, but here
interestingly it's Dharmakirti who
says the thing about what makes the seed
fatter okay, so here we go ... ,SRID PA'I SRED LAS
RNAM BRGAL BA'I, ... he's talking about link 8
and link 9, which in the rebirth process
is heavy misunderstanding just before
you die, heavy misunderstanding just
before you die, and it makes the seeds
strong enough to throw a new rebirth
okay, which is number 11, okay got it?
So, he says you want to stop negative
seeds from growing right?
By the way, do the four powers stop
negative seeds, do they destroy negative
seeds? No, they just put them in the
freezer,
and then they put a lock on it and it
never opens, you can't destroy a negative
seed like that, why? There's a justice to
the universe, if those who hurt people
must get hurt, those who help people must
get help
you can't magically just say, "oh here
your sins are gone" you know," good luck"
you know, you can't do that. You always
get ... it's like gravity okay got it?
Okay, ,SRID PA'I SRED LAS, so how Dharmakirti
says how do you stop a bad seed,
how do you shut down a bad seed, how do
you get the guys in the factory to go
back to sleep?
,LAS GZHAN 'PHEN NUS MA YIN TE,
means the karma will not be able to
throw any results okay, if you can shut
down the factory of a bad seed, okay got
it?
Understand? Nod, okay, no don't nod
because you're falling asleep, what? ... [speaks in Russian]
Yeah ... does it destroy the seed you
mean?
Oh, yeah the seed still planted ... no, it
still gets planted, but weakly weakly,
not as strong okay, especially if you're
thinking I wouldn't do it again okay,
it's called the morning-after pill ...
seriously,
okay, after you do something wrong, if you
decide you wouldn't do it again, it
pretty much kills the power, that's the
guts of the four powers. Okay anyway,
,LHAN CIG BYED PA ZAD PHYIR RO, very
beautiful ... LHAN CIG BYED RKYEN for $50 ...
Word's like ... LHAN CIG BYED RKYEN?
BYED RKYEN.  LHAN CIG BYED RKYEN. RKYEN.
I'll give you a clue for $25 ...
Yeah nice, as opposed to NYER LEN GYI GYU
okay, "material cause" of the tree is the
seed, LHAN CIG BYED RKYEN means the conditions,
like the water, and the fertilizer, okay?
And Dharmakiriti, Ok $25 for him
Shaoping,
... she's my banker this week okay, she
got all the money honey, alright ...
LHAN CIG BYED PA ZAD PHYIR RO,
ZAD PHYIR RO means you killed the conditions, not the
seed okay, you killed the conditions not
the seed,
okay, he's talking about how do you kill
bad seeds, and he says look don't go
after the seed, don't go after the seed,
go after the water, go after the sunlight,
but ... like I have weeds in my garden you
know what I do? You have a choice, you can
sit there and try to pull them out all
day, it's it's back-breaking work,
it's terrible work, my gardener refuses
to do it okay, or you can just put a
piece of plywood over them and they die,
because they don't get sun okay?
You didn't change the seeds, you didn't
take out the plant,
you cut the LHAN CIG BYED RKYEN,
you cut the supporting condition okay? So, Dharmakirti
is saying do it that way,
okay, do it that way, cut the support for
the negative seed okay, go after the
support, it's easier than trying to fight
with the seed okay, alright ... ZHES DANG,
SRED PA NI,
,YOD NA SLAR YANG 'BYUNG PHYIR RO,
if you don't do that, and you still have
that SRED PA, the big seed's going to grow, the
factory is going to open okay?
Now, SRED PA is technically the name for
the eighth link okay, they call
"initial desire" and then number nine, what's
it? DGU PA LEN PA, "advanced desire"
okay, so eight is called technically in
The Wheel of Life teaching, [link] eight is called
"beginning desire" and nine is called
"advanced desire", and eight or nine are
the sunlight for the seeds that are
going to throw you into another rebirth in
suffering, okay got it?
So, question for you okay question for
you, I'm in the third turning of the
wheel, are you serious? Is this really
what you mean to say? I should stop
wanting things and my bad seeds won't
open? Is that ... is that what it is Geshela?
Initial desire and advanced desire, is it
really number eight and number nine that
makes number ten open into number
eleven? Is it really? The answer is no!
It's not, desire is not the problem.
What's the problem? It's not
understanding okay, well then why in the
teaching on the twelve links do they
have the two sunlights called
beginning desire and advanced desire, why
do they call it desire? ... That's part of the
answer,
what [turning of the] wheel is the teaching on the wheel?
Hmm? Yeah, it's the list period. He's like,
"oh, there's 12 links", you know? He didn't get to?
Emptiness yet, okay got it? So, the
wheel teaching is very ... Abhidharma
okay,
the first great presentation of the
wheel is Abhidharma, why am I talking
about that? I spent two hours last night
trying to talk about the different ideas
of the different schools okay,
who taught those schools? Buddha, okay, are they
correct?
No! Only one okay? Why did Buddha teach
something that's not correct? Yeah, it pushes
the student a little higher, okay it
pushes the student a little higher okay, it's
helpful, it's not a cure, okay got it?
So, now in this Lamrim, Pabongkha Rinpoche
talking to farmers, is saying desire
causes the bad seeds to open, and if you
can cut that sunlight the seeds will
never open, got it? Okay? It's an
introduction to the topic of "klesha" [mental afflictions],
who said that? You should wait until I
offer money, perfect answer!
Okay, if you're gonna bring up kleshas, if
you want to talk about kleshas, then talk
about how you can kill your bad seeds if
you don't have them. The factory will
never open, the factory will never wake
up okay, so he's trying to get us to the
next section of the lamrim, which is
the study of the wind that disturbed the
glassy water of your mind this morning,
okay got it?
Cool? How did we get there? Through school
number two, Dharmakirti okay, which is
really cool. If you study enough you
start to suspect that all these lower
school guys are actually higher school,
and they're just playing along with the
Buddha okay?
SRED PA NI,
,YOD NA SLAR YANG 'BYUNG PHYIR RO,
and ... if you have the sunlight,
meaning if you don't understand the seeds,
not only will it open this seed, but it
will? It ... itself will plant new seeds.
Okay, it's a nasty, it's almost like a ...
self-perpetuating wheel ... okay, you
misunderstand the seed, it opens, and when
you misunderstand it you plant new seeds
to open later,
okay got it? It's like trying to talk to
your wife okay ... right ... no he
doesn't have this problem.
Okay, DES NA 'KHOR BA SKYED BYED KYI RTZA BA NI NYON MONGS NYID YIN NO,
Therefore, the very root, NYID right? The
very root that spins this wheel, 'KHOR BA, is ...
NYON MONGS. Kleshas. NYID, that and nothing
else. NYID means "that and nothing else"
okay, so we got to talk about, we got to
study the bad parts of our mind, all
week long we got to try to bring, up in
the peaceful mind, bring up crap on
purpose okay?
It's going to be a depressing week okay,
got it? Alright, here we go ... he said, just
now, the whole trigger that starts the
Wheel of Life is kleshas, yeah we got to
talk about it okay, we got to talk about
it okay. I didn't forget your question
Steven, I'm still thinking about it.
Okay .... now hundred dollars!
I'm going to run out of money really soon ...
someone who knows Tibetan, a few people
here, tell me what this next paragraph is
for $100. I just want one word, it's so
easy it's like 10 ... it's $10 a letter.
Time's up!
Let's read it together ...
say, NYON MONGS
ZHES PA RANG NAM SKYES MA THAG TU,
RANG STOBS KYIS RANG RGYUD LDAN GYI GANG ZAG SEMS RGYUD MA ZHI ZHING MA DUL BAR
BYED PA'I BYED LAS CAN.
NYON MONGS GI MTSAN NYID.
Definition of Klesha! I gave it to you this morning,
this is the cheapest hundred dollars
you ever could have gotten, definition of
klesha, definition of a negative thought
okay, here it is, you got it this morning
okay ...rang dang tsungden gyi semgyu ma-shiwar jepay rikne kyi semjung
very famous okay, he made it a
little Lamrimmy, you know he made it
easier, okay. Here we go, ready ... NYON MONGS ZHES PA okay, this thing we call "klesha",
this thing we call klesha,
RANG NAM SKYES MA THAG TU, this NAM by the way
Word, this means "when", "when", yeah it's
very unusual okay, just after you get one
okay, just after it enters your mind, this
wind okay
RANG SKYES MA THAG TU, RANG NAM SKYES MA THAG TU, just after it comes in your mind,
RANG STOBS KYIS ... yeah "by its own power",
nobody else has to do anything okay,
automatically, what happens?
RANG RGYUD LDAN GYI GANG ZAG
the person who has it in their mind,
SEMS RGYUD their mind MA ZHI
yeah, ashanti okay, no shanti [peace],
their mind gets stirred up, the wind ruins
your peace of mind, like you were having a
good day until I told you to think about
your old boyfriend right? Then
then you've got off balance okay, that
off balance is very crucial in Buddhist
practice okay, DCI level 10 Taiwan, one
month ago Stanley, yeah it's the
fertilizer for anger okay, your mind just
gets off balance, see? Like you ... you
were having a good day and then I
mentioned the old boyfriend and you're
like ... you were like this, and then you
went ... and you kind of get a little off
balance. That's the breeding ground,
that's the feeding place, for klesha.
Kleshas love it when you get off balance
okay, so really we want to study how to
not get off balance and then the klesha
can't come anyway okay, there's no food
in the mind, okay got it?
Here we go my MA ZHI ZHING, he adds
something here ... MA DUL, MA DUL,
DUL yeah, the mind starts acting crazy
like a crazy horse okay, MA DUL, Sanskrit?
No vinaya, no vinaya, here's the word okay,
it means when you think about the
ex-boyfriend two things happen,
(1) choppy water (2) you
start acting crazy,
you will ... five minutes after you think
about your old boyfriend you're more
likely to say something bad to another
person okay, it makes you ... wild horsey,
it makes the mind wild horse okay, got it?
ZHI ZHING MA DUL BAR BYED PA'I BYED LAS CAN,
that's the function of a klesha, we define
klesha by its function, two functions:
(1) it throws you off balance,
okay (2) you start acting crazy
okay, you start acting MA DUL, like a
wild horse okay, got it? Then you're gonna
have all kinds of problems okay, if we
followed Dharmakirti,
what would Dharmakirti add here?
Yeah, it's gonna feed your negative seeds, it's
gonna feed, it's gonna act as sunlight
and water for your negative seeds, if
Dharmakirti had written this
definition, he would have added: it feeds
your negative seeds, it helps them to
grow, it's the fertilizer okay, now don't
go after the seed, do what?
cut the fertilizer, cut the
sunlight okay, put a board over the weeds
they'll die, they don't get Sun, they need ...
that's their food, okay got it?
So, this whole week we're gonna study about how to starve your ... how to stop your kleshas and
starve your seeds, got it?
Okay cool? It's not just that you become
a happier person, it's that your all your
bad seeds are choked off, they don't have
food, they don't have the food they need,
Mr. Steven, don't ...
Yeah, they are, they're saying the ...
by the way, the klesha is "sem",
mind, consciousness, and the seed is
potential, it's not mental, so that's a
trick you learn in DCI, it ... how do you
say it in DCI, do you remember? A
seed ... when I ask you, is a seed mental,
what's the answer? But, what's the full
answer? Hmm? Yeah, good! It lives in the
mind, but it doesn't think, it's not aware,
therefore it's not mind,
it's not made of mind, it lives in the
mind as a potential, technically a
changing thing which is neither physical
nor mental,
it's a potential, it's ... it's a thing, but
it's not mind itself, because it doesn't
think, it's not aware, got it? If ... if
something is mind it must suck in
objects, it must be aware of objects, but
seeds are not, seeds are like sleepy
little guys waiting to wake up, they are
not mind, but they live in the mind ok
got it? Alright, that's the answer to your
question, but it's a cool question and
it's a cool answer. Alright, at this point
we go to your meditation book ok? You
have a special meditation book, if you
don't have a meditation book they're over
here in the box, am i right?
Ok, this is a little book of your
meditations for the week okay, guess what
the first one is, what's the picture? It
should be some water stirred up,
isn't it?
Ok yeah, not glassy water ok, not glassy
water ok, and we did that meditation this
morning so, in the afternoon after yoga,
after a heavy lunch, you're going to go home and?
Sleep! After your nap, you might want
to do this meditation again ok, because
you're supposed to be on retreat ok?
And even people in retreat take naps ok,
somebody told me ... I'm reading a book
about getting married,
and they say, don't expect life to be
different after you get married then
before you get married, there's nothing
special about a half hour ceremony that's
suddenly going to change both of you, see what I
mean, why did I say that?
Oh, just because you're in retreat
doesn't mean you can't take naps ok, the
fact that you're in retreat is not going to
change your your daily habits ok, so go ...
go with the flow, do a good yoga, over-eat,
crash, then go to your meditation book
okay, before the evening class okay, or if
you're in the teacher training good luck.
Okay, do your homework ... okay, and that Idim,
which we call ... what's it? "Idea image", we
made a new word Idim, say Idim, idea image
okay,
we're studying the lamrim through idea
images, and this is one ... it's easier to
remember, it's like Chinese characters
are easier to remember because they ... in
ancient times, the turtle characters,
turtle shell characters, they looked a
little bit like the thing they're
supposed to represent okay, so it it's
more powerful in the subconscious okay,
alright, which is why Chinese are so
smart okay ...
next paragraph, DE YANG NGOS ZIN DGOS KYI, NGOS MA ZIN NA DGRA NGOS MA ZIN PAR ...
NGOS ZIN, Word for ... I don't know 30 dollars ...
damn, $30 more. I'm gonna make you stop
talking after awhile. DE YANG NGOS ZIN, what do
you have to listen? Guess. Yeah, you gotta
be able to recognize when the waters
getting choppy, that's the name of the
game
okay? Huh, oh Geshela? What? My water's
getting choppy right now okay, if you
don't know what it looks like you can't
fight it okay,
you've got to meditate, this first
meditation, we'll do it again tomorrow
okay, you got to know what it feels like
when the water goes from glassy to
choppy, because that's when you've got to
do something okay, don't wait until
you're angry okay,
when you feel the mind ... little bit
uncomfortable stop, you know, go sit down
you know, have some green drink,
calm yourself down, don't let it get
worse, you see I mean? You got to be able
to recognize the baby stages of a klesha,
and it's "off balance" okay,
study your own mind it's the purpose of
meditation, get to recognize what it
feels like when your mind goes from
smooth to a little bit ... off balance, and the
way you do that: this week during your
meditation think of somebody who's a
problem nowadays in your life, do it
quick because next week is gonna be
somebody else okay, alright?
Get used to what it feels like when you
start thinking about someone you don't
like. Get used to, listen, recognize what
it feels like ... it feels ... how does it feel?
How would you say it? How would you say
it huh?
Not quiet, what's another one, how do you
feel when you start thinking about
someone you don't like? Agitated, what? Yeah,
I would say that also, what do you say in
Spanish? Incómodo,
incómodo yeah, you start feeling like ...
you know, and that's just before you say
something, or just before you get angry, you know,
you get like ... I don't know ... okay watch my
face ... that's what it is, okay got it? So,
you ... you gotta learn to recognize the
thought behind the face, there's a
thought behind the face you know, and you
gotta be super sensitive to that okay,
any fool knows when they're angry okay,
that's not ... you don't have to be a
Buddhist okay, "I'm angry", yeah a Buddhist
can detect the warning signs of anger ...
I'm gonna get angry in three minutes, if
I don't deal with this I start to feel ...
"that guy can't believe what he said the
other day,
he also said, ..." okay, you gotta be able to
NGOS ZIN, you know, "oh I'm getting a
klesha, I'm gonna have a klesha in two
minutes", okay that's Buddhist practice
okay,
that's Buddhism okay, I'm gonna have a
kleshe in two minutes, I better do
something okay, have a nice coffee or
something, change the mood you know, do
something, I'll tell you a really cool
trick ... if you're in a room and you're
having a problem with somebody and it's
getting intense okay,
drop a cup on purpose, full cup of green
drink ... glass everywhere, green drink
everywhere, it takes 20 minutes to clean
it up, everybody forgets about their
klesha, try it, it's really fun. ok ...
definitely, or take your pants off or
something, I'm telling you everyone
forgets about what the argument was, they're like,
"what!" You know, okay now whichever one is
more comfortable ... this could get weird.
Okay, alright, NGOS MA ZIN PAR
GSOD BYED KYI MDA' 'PHEN PA BZHIN,
otherwise, you are like an archer who's trying to shoot a
target, but doesn't know what's the
target.
Okay, and it comes back to our
blind lady from yesterday, if you can't
see the target how are you gonna hit it
okay? If you don't know what it looks
like when a klesha is starting, how are
you gonna stop it okay? You gotta get in
touch with what it feels like just five
minutes before you get angry okay, you
got to get in touch with your own mind
and be able to ring the smoke alarm,
"sheshin" ... when you start to get upset
you get off balance, you're not upset yet
you're just like ... like someone says
"you're idiot" you know, and you're like ...
... what?!? You know, like just before you
understand the word, you start to feel
uncomfortable, that's where we're gonna
shoot the arrow, then, don't wait until he's
too big to kill, you can't stop anger in
the middle of anger, forget it you know, go
take a walk, get away from the person,
we're gonna study lower methods of
removing kleshas, one of them is: avoid
the person, you know, arrange your life so
you never meet them okay, but if you
don't know what they look like you can't
hit the ... okay you gotta be able ... to shoot an
arrow you have to know what the target
looks like okay, got it? Okay, 'PHEN PA BZHIN,
GANG LA GNYEN PO BSTEN DGOS PA MI SHES PAS, DANG PO NYON MONGS NGOS GZUNG BA LA GNYIS,
so I'm gonna teach you how to
recognize that you're getting a klesha,
okay, I'm gonna ... actually he's gonna
introduce us to the whole study of
kleshas, so it's a depressing week I'm
sorry, there's nothing nice about the
whole week okay, we're gonna study
kleshas, we're gonna become klesha
masters, you already were ... but now you're
gonna know why, okay klesha master okay,
and there's two divisions two kleshas.
Now, this is a study of twenty six
kleshas, six major, twenty secondary, six
main kleshas that everybody has, and
twenty kleshas that you have, you know a
couple of times a week, six that you have
a thousand times every day, twenty that you
have a couple of times every week okay,
they're called the primary negative
emotions and the secondary negative
emotions, now you are so lucky that two of
our translators have translated this
section, one from the Abhidharma, and one
from the Mind-Only.
So, Word translated it in his mind-only
text and Stanley translated it in his
Abhidharma text, so I asked Stanley if,
his permission to use his translation, he
said yes, so we'll give it to you
tomorrow or the next day okay, it's about
thirteen pages of negativities okay.
Can you send Tim yours? Yours is more of a
chart, so send him the chart okay,
and you can add that to ... where's Tim, you
can add it to Stanley's thing okay, okay
cool?
Because, Pabongkha Rinpoche doesn't give
you the 20 ... why? His thousand-page book
would become to 3,000 pages okay, he had
to cut it, he was not teaching Geshes, he
was teaching farmers, and they cut it
okay, but you are Geshes, you are baby
Geshes, so we're gonna go through his
six main kleshas with him, but then we're
gonna go to the 20 classes from Stanley
and Word, who have so kindly translated, the strategy of our translation
team is that we have one translator on
each great school and sub school, so we
have about ... we're working on 18 texts at
the same time, but from every different
school okay cool? Cool ma?
Okay, here we go ... so thank the translators
if you see them, and the next picture in
your meditation book is really learning
at least the six, learn their names, learn
what they look like, so you can shoot
them okay, get to know the crap in your
own mind okay, probably you're familiar
with three of them,
and probably three of them are running
around and you don't really notice it
okay, so the goal today and tomorrow,
learn the main six and find them in your
own mind,
that's meditation, that's real meditation,
Oh Geshela, I wanted to do some emptiness
meditation, yeah that's fine but
do this one first okay?
Learn to recognize your own kleshas,
because you've been living with them for
about a billion lifetimes, they were
running around in your mind and you
didn't even notice it
okay, but your friends did  ...okay right?
Okay, so when you do meditation ... we'll do
meditation number two ... after we learn the
six okay, and we'll go on a ...
excuse me, but we'll go on a crap trip.
We'll try to locate these six in your
own mind okay, they're there you haven't
met some of them,
you didn't recognize, NGOS GZUNG, okay? Okay,
here we go ...
RTZA NYON DANG, NYE NYON NO, RTZA NYON DANG, NYE NYON NO,
back to the text ...
RTZA NYON DANG, NYE NYON ...
say RTZA NYON. NYE NYON. RTZA NYON. NYE NYON. RTZA NYON .... Stanley?
RTZA NYON? TZAWA. NYON MONGS?
Yeah, "root kleshas" okay? Six, the big six then NYE NYON,
NYE NYON means the 20, yeah like
assistant kleshas okay, six main ones that
we have many times every day, twenty that
we have from time to time, okay cool alright.
GZUNG BA LA and he cheats us by the way, he
says, I'm gonna make two presentations
here: (1) the six main negative
emotions and secondly, I'll give you the
twenty secondary emotions, but if you
study this text, you can check the
Chinese translation, he left out the 20,
Err, he promises them here, he says first
I'll give you this, second ... and then he
never does the 20 okay, so we're taking
it from Stanley and Word okay,
alright, MDZOD, say MDZOD LAS, he's quoting MDZOD,
which in Sanskrit is? Kosha, the treasure
house, which means? The Abhidharma
okay, Vasubhandu, first one I taught
you yesterday, first great book
okay, he's he's going to the first great
book, which is really the mother book
okay, of all basic Buddhist fun ...
information okay, which is why Stanley
won't finish until 2042, 2046? Six, yeah I
will be 96, something like that, Om Mani Padme Hung,
okay, alright. Okay, here's the
verse from the from the Abhidharma, I
think it's the fifth chapter ...
,SRID PA'I RTZA BA PHRA RGYAS DRUG,
(1) 'DOD CHAGS DE BZHIN (2) KHONG KHRO DANG,
,(3) NGA RGYAL (4) MA RIG (5) LTA BA DANG, (6) THE TSOM YIN TE,
Here's the presentation from the Abhidharma on the six main negative emotions okay, ,SRID PA'I RTZA BA, these  are the
root of?  Sipay Korlo, Bhavachakra, the Wheel of Life, SRID PA'I RTZA BA,
DRUG, and there's six of them ... then he says PHRA RGYAS, this is an Abhidharma word for NYON MONGS,
this is a special Abhidharma word for
klesha
okay, it's a different word okay, PHRA RGYAS ...
$50, two pieces of this word, it's a ...
ok i'l give you a clue,
it's ... yeah you already got it, just slow
down! Don't answer the question until I
ask it ... we're talking about an alternate
name for "negative emotion", it's an ... it's
an alternate name for klesha, and it's
the name that the Abhidharma uses, and
that's why our translation team splits
up by school, because the the word for
negative emotion in Abhidharma
is different than the word for negative
emotion in the middle way school, and so
we specialize our translators,
some translators are specializing in
Abhidharma, that's Stanley,
some people specializing in Mind Only,
that's Word, some people specializing in
Vinaya which is Shaoping okay, so PHRA, PHRA
means? "Subtle". RGYAS means? "Everywhere", the
word for klesha in the Abhidharma
school is "everywhere", the "subtle
everywhere" ... the subtle
everywhere, what's it mean? You got them
all ... they're everywhere in your mind, your
mind is infected, the cancer has
metastasized, it's it's spread all through
your mind, RGYAS, and it's PHRA, it's hard to
detect sometimes, it's hard to detect, you
have cancer and you don't know okay, the
doctors couldn't find it yet, okay and
for Abhidharma,
for Vasubhandu, this is the nature of a
negative emotion, they have already
infected your whole mind, RGYAS, and they
are PHRA RGYAS, they're subtle, they're hard to
detect, you can have a klesha going on
all day and you think you're having a
good day okay, actually just have a
low-level desire for coffee all day ...
mmm okay, so he says the root of samsara,
the root of suffering, is these six big
kleshas, subtle ... subtle everywheres okay,
here they are, here's the list, okay, get
to know them, you know them already but you
don't know them, you don't recognize them okay.
'DOD CHAGS, say 'DOD CHAGS. Desire. number one okay, KHONG KHRO anger number two okay,
NGA RGYAL,
give me the pieces of it, anybody except
Word ... yeah, NGA means "me",  RGYAL means what?
RGYAL PO, "I'm a king", we had a great
boxer in my generation called Muhammad
Ali and he would always say "I'm the
greatest, I'm the greatest", you know, and he
was, anyway the word for "pride" in
Buddhism is "I'm the greatest" okay, NGA RGYAL, I'm the king okay, that's number
three okay, number four ... MA RIG PA ...
misunderstanding, give that man $100!
I don't know if he got ... yeah he did,
50 there, but Ven. Phil gets a
$100 because he didn't say ... ignorance
okay, which is how everybody translates
that word, it's wrong! Okay,
ignorance means not knowing and the
Abhidharma specifically says that's not
what causes the problem,
it's misunderstanding, it's mis-knowing,
it's not not being aware, it's mis-being-aware
okay got it?
It's not that you didn't see your friend, it's
that you kissed the wrong guy,
understand got it? It's a big difference
right, don't kiss anybody or kiss the
wrong guy, we're talking about kissing
the wrong guy, that causes trouble,
try it Shaoping and see okay ... that's
MA RIG PA, misunderstanding okay, not
ignorance, I don't know who made ignorance,
okay forget that.
Okay, LTA BA, number five ...huh? Yeah, how you see
the world, how you see the world, world-view okay, how do you see the world okay,
and there's ... that's one of the main
mistakes. Now, you should be asking me a
question, yeah ... good, why you make two
different ones Geshe-la, I mean Vasubhandu,
why you say
number four is? Misunderstanding and then
you say number five is how you view the
world, because isn't it the same thing?
It's not, we're gonna get to it okay, but
it's a good question, if you if the
question came up in your mind you are
not asleep.
Okay number six,
THE TSOM, doubt, and we ... and when you teach
your students about the Buddhist concept
of doubt, you always have to say?
A certain kind of doubt, god bless you, yeah.
You should wait til I offer money okay,
yeah ... it's not a klesha to question the
teacher and the teaching, it's not a
klesha to question the teacher and to
question the teaching, that's healthy,
that's healthy, Geshela, I don't
understand the difference between four and
five, I mean first you say
misunderstanding and then you say how
you view the world, I don't get it, why ...
why two different ones?
That's a doubt right? That's number six
but it's not okay, why it's not a klesha?
Why? It's healthy okay,
if a student asked why did you repeat
number four number five it means they're
still away, and that's a good thing
got it okay, if they don't ask me why you
repeated misunderstanding twice, it means
they're asleep or ... I mean on some level
okay got it?
so THE TSOM can be a great thing okay,
and we're gonna study doubt, ?
? something, you can
check, uh, we're gonna study what's good
doubt and what's a bad doubt okay, what's
the klesha of doubt, and what's the
healthy doubt okay, because if you don't
doubt you're not a debater and you don't
belong in a Tsongkapa room okay, got
it?
Which implies, that you should encourage
doubt as a teacher okay, when you become
a teacher, ACI teacher, and you're
teaching people and you got some nudnik,
okay this is Jewish word ... irritating
student who keeps asking questions, a
poorly-trained teacher will get offended
and try to shut them down, don't ... don't
ask so many questions Stephen I ... I
don't understand that one yet,
okay ... so a poorly-trained teacher will
avoid questions, they'll try to get
people not to talk, not to ask questions
okay? A well-trained teacher is like ...
cool Stephen you're still thinking, you're
in the class, you're thinking, I'm ... I
appreciate it, thank you, and I don't
quite have an answer yet, got it, about
why this misunderstanding .... okay
I'm working on it,
this part's working on it okay, got it?
So, the subject of doubt, to study
doubt, is a cool thing
okay, what's a good doubt and what's a bad
doubt, what's the one here? It's a bad doubt,
it's some kind of doubt that's hurting
you okay got it, what it is
by the way, I'll just tell you in advance
in case we all die this afternoon, it's
being a donkey, how do you say po-russki
donkey? Oсел [in Russian], 驢 (Lǘ) [Chinese] okay ...
it's being a donkey,
it means the teacher told you clearly it
was correct, everything was fine, and
you're like still "I don't know, I don't
know if I want to do that" you know, "yeah
I understand a thing about meditating
one minute more every week but you know
I don't know if it's gonna work", that's
bad doubt okay got it?
Alright, bad doubt is lazy, we're gonna go
for one more minute I'm gonna give you a ...
it's not a pee-pee break, it's a walk
around and stretch break, you don't have
to do the green and the pen but you do
have to stretch okay, you need it, these
classes in the morning are really long,
why are they so long? The morning is the
best time to think, I'm taking you're
thinking time then you go sleep in the
afternoon I don't care. Okay, RTZA NYON DRUG LAS,
DANG PO 'DOD CHAGS NI, let's go on a
trip to the subject of desire, first of
the sixth okay, let's go on a trip,
let's explore desire, what is desire okay,
ready?
YUL YID DU 'ONG BA NOR DANG LUS, ZAS SKOM SOGS MTHONG BA NA ... when you see attractive things
okay, when you see [DMIGS] attractive things like
money, like $100 for answering a
question,
or LUS, oh I have such a beautiful strong
Yoga body you know, woo okay, or ZAS yeah,
oh look at that you know sweet roll,
SKOM, here it means beverage okay, you
know, oh look a nice cappuccino okay,
food and drink etc. [SOGS], 10,000 other things,
MTHONG BA NA, when you see them, DE LA DMIGS NAS,
when you focus on them,
DE DANG MI 'BRAL BAR 'DOD, you don't want to 'BRAL ...
you never want to lose it, you don't want
to lose it okay, this is MY coffee, this
is MY hundred dollar question, answer
okay, I don't ... this is MY Yoga body you
know okay, I want I don't want to lose it
okay.
MI 'BRAL BAR 'DOD means "I don't want to
lose it", SEMS PA that thought is desire
okay? ... Now, crucial question, if you answer
it I'll give you a break, if you don't
you have to keep going. If you don't
answer it I'll answer it because I need a break okay.
Higher school or lower
school? Why? Ahh! Hundred dollars!
That one okay, say it again ... yeah, it's not
wrong to want nice things, it's not
Buddhism to tell people don't have nice
cappuccinos then you're a Buddhist you
know, don't want to have a healthy body,
Yoga body, then you're a Buddhist okay,
don't ever enjoy money and never buy a
new car, don't ever buy anything you
enjoy okay, that's Buddhism. Higher school or
lower school? low low low low low low low
low okay, really low school, you'd think
those Buddha's in those buddha paradises
are avoiding cappuccinos? Come on! They
got this big smile on their face you
know, the paintings are always ... look at
this paradise you know, this is fruits,
these are all special meanings, the mirror is ...
the mirror represents all beautiful
things you could ever see okay, it's in
the Buddha paradise okay, is that desire?
If it is then Buddhist is still ... then
this is a Wheel of Life painting,
understand okay? If desire is ...
if wanting things is wrong then you
shouldn't want Buddhahood, you shouldn't
want to help all the people in the
universe, you shouldn't look at the Stars
ever okay, so Jasso's answer, he
doesn't answer as often as Word, but
his the answers are better ... just kidding ...
okay lower school, definitely lower school
okay, what ... what do you have to add to
make it higher school? ... Yeah, in a wrong
way, misunderstanding, is it wrong to want
a new Tesla Model X car? It's not, if
everyone could have one, that's okay, or
do you want a world without any
beautiful things? Is the goal of a
bodhisattva to make sure everybody has
nothing equally?
You see? Is that what Buddhism is? You see
what I mean, or do you want everyone to
have a model X Tesla and there's
enough highways, and they're all running
on 100% solar okay, got it?
That's a bodhisattva okay got it?
So, be careful when you ... he's teaching a
lower definition of desire okay,
desire ... oftentimes in ACI, in DCI, in our
translations we add the word "ignorant
desire" okay, just because
misunderstanding is there it's kind of
weird okay, describe ignorant desire with
a cappuccino, somebody for zero dollars?
You had the last one ... yeah, what? You would
take the last one and? Drink all of it,
that's all okay, what's intelligent
desire?
Yeah! Good, if I had more money I would
give you I promise .... okay, sharing is
intelligent desire okay,
intelligent desire, there's nothing wrong
with intelligent desire okay, share ... I like cappuccino ... i like this so much I'm gonna give it
to Jasso! What? Are you crazy? No, you're
crazy, you don't understand where
cappuccinos come from okay, I love cappuccinos so much so I'm gonna make sure
everyone in the room has one, I like
suffering so much I'm gonna make sure we
have green drinks ... okay, we're gonna take
a break there, take a 10-minute
break, come back by 10:20 how's that? 10:20 please okay, and go stretch, you don't
have to do the green ... okay, we're gonna
start, we have about another half hour,
it's the longest half hour because
you're tired, so be tough okay, be a
little tough.
I'll be tough too and we're gonna keep
going on the on the ... on this lamrim, tomorrow
if I have time to get it ready, we'll
start the review we've been doing of the
eight years that we did so far, so we're
we're doing about a half hour everyday
review of the past eight years, so if
there were retreats that you didn't come
to, it's a chance to get some of the past
eight years
ok, alright mmm ... DPER NA NYON MONGS GZHAN
RAS LA RDUL ZHUGS PA LTAR DBYUNG SLA YANG, okay so I have an old lady that
I take care of and ... I take her ... once a
month I take her to dinner and a movie,
and ... I took her to the ballet last Sunday
and ... then we went for dinner and I'm ... and
let's say she had spaghetti okay, so
there's two parts to spaghetti, there's
the noodles and there's the sauce right?
And ... she always wears white clothes when
we go out, I don't know why ... and I don't
know when you get to be 93 you don't
notice if things fall off your fork or
not you know, like she'll drop everything
and then she'll say ... you know, did I eat
that already or not? So ... there's a
difference between spaghetti and tomato
sauce you see, the noodles, if you drop
them on your white pants after the ballet,
it's not such a big deal, you just take
it off right, and it doesn't leave much
of a stain okay, but ... if the spaghetti
sauce drops on your white pants ... it makes
a stain and ... if they used a lot of olive
oil,
it starts to spread okay, so by the time
we got home she had like ... she looked like
she'd been in a war or something, and she's all
red and ... I don't say anything I just wash
her clothes you know, so ... DPER NA NYON MONGS GZHAN,
other kinds of kleshas, RAS LA RDUL ZHUGS PA LTAR, are like some dust on your pants,
you know and you can just go like like
this ... right? You can just shake it off,
like the spaghetti noodle without the
sauce okay, DBYUNG SLA, difficult Tibetan
here, you got it?
DBYUNG SLA ... easy to get throw, off easy to get
off okay,
'DOD CHAGS NI, but desire ... but desire YUL LA
ZHEN CING CHAGS PA, it wants ... it's attached,
and RAS LA SNUM ZHUGS PA, and it's like the
spaghetti sauce with lots of olive oil,
and SNUM GYIS JE CHER KHYAB, and it will start
to spread okay, if you don't clean it off
right away it'll start to ... that stain
will get wider and wider okay? So desire's
like that, DBYUNG DKA' BA BZHIN, it has two
qualities if you think about it,
(1) the nature of not sharing is
that it gets worse, people who don't want
to share today, they don't want to share
more tomorrow you see, it gets bigger and
bigger. So, first you don't want to share
your ... cappuccino, then you don't want to
share your car, and then you don't want
to share your money, and then you don't
want to share your time, and it gets
worse and worse okay, it's like the olive
oil ... it tends to spread okay, the
habit of not sharing
tends to increase okay, it's it's nature
of desire, it's different from other
kleshas and YUL BLTA BA, very difficult
to get out of the human mind okay,
very difficult to extract it from the
human mind ... there's a big subject in
Word'ss Mind-Only text, extremely
interesting big subject, you want to
explain it, you got a microphone? For $0 ...
he's gonna explain ... I want you to
explain the the brain operation thing
okay, ... five minutes or ten, I don't care,
I'll take a break ...
you give a nice little ... lecture ...
earn your keep ... ok
they have
okay
okay so you kno w went over and then and
then you made all these clarifications
positions
I'd like to say I'd like to say when are
you done I'm sorry
do you have to completely destroy your
body because Martin or is it possible
just to extract those problems to your
mind like a surgeon would extract the
tumor from a cancer patient while
keeping the healthy tissue okay and so
and so then the discussion is once you
become an archive in a lower school or a
bodhisattva on the eighth level which is
in the higher school
what's uh what's the ants in the
epidermis cool when you reach nirvana
what happens to your mind yeah yeah good
when you cut out the glaciers you
disappear
that's nirvana abhidhamma in other words
when the surgeon cuts out the tumor they
cut out the brain also
I think the the thing in your text that
I learned the most from is very
interesting, see they say you have a
seventh and an eighth part of your mind,
only mind only school says that, you have
your six senses and your awareness of
your six senses, including your thinking
okay, but Mind Only school says you have
number seven and you have an eight.
Seven is all your kleshas, all the bag
of kleshas in your mind, and then number
eight is the refrigerator where you keep
all your seeds, alaya vijnyana okay,
storehouse, the refrigerator were all
your seeds stay.
Why does Mind Only school say that when
your husband yells at you ... he's not
outside?
yeah
so, if we go deeper than the lamrim okay,
if we go deeper than the lamrim, the
reason you get a klesha is that you
look at the refrigerator and you don't
understand it ... maybe that answers your
question ... okay?
Mind Only school okay, I'll say it again
they have two extra parts of your mind,
we call number seven and number eight,
that the other schools don't talk about
okay, number seven is all your negative
emotions, all your kleshas. Number eight
is the refrigerator where your seeds are
stored, and when they open okay, when did
you plant the seed for your husband
yelling? When you yelled at your kids
last week, you put a seed in the
refrigerator when you yelled at your
kids last week, how? Good, by being aware
of yourself, by hearing your own bad
words okay, it's not that God wrote down
"oh you get a seed, you yelled at your
kids", it's not like that, what plants a
seed is you hear your own talk okay, and that
plants a seed in your mind okay, the seed
was put in the refrigerator,
consciousness number? Eight, last week and
then this week the seed opened where? In
the refrigerator okay,
higher school says the seed open outside,
okay Mind Only school says the seed
opened in your own mind, your husband is
yelling in your own mind, you're watching
a video in your own mind, got it? But the
thing that got me most excited about
your text ... was that seven is
misunderstanding eight, and maybe that
helps with your question Stephen, seven
is misunderstanding eight,
the kleshas are only possible if you
misunderstand where your husband is, in
the refrigerator,
and that's the whole process of
liberation and samsara in the Mind Only
school, it's the interaction between 7
and 8. 7 is looking at the seeds
open in 8 and thinks the husband is
out in the kitchen and that he decided
to yell at you got it? This is Mind Only
version of nirvana and it's cool, it's
not bad. I'll say it again, you have a bag
of negative emotions in your mind, that's
called "nyod nye",  "bag of negative emotion mind",
and then you got "kun gzhi", alaya vijnyana,
foundation consciousness, the
refrigerator where all the seeds live
okay, last week you yelled at your kids,
by hearing yourself yell, you put an
imprint in the refrigerator, okay got
it?
So, in the Mind Only school what's
keeping you out of nirvana, and which
causes you to have anger, is that number
seven doesn't understand number eight,
got it?
Number seven looks at the video in your
own mind and thinks the husband decided
to yell at you, got it? If ... now, what's the
function of Buddhist practice in the
Mind Only school, somebody tell me
in ... using seven and eight, what does
the Mind Only school want you to do in
Buddhist practice? Huh? Yeah, but how do
you destroy seven? Yeah, you just see what
the hell's going on in the eight, oh the
husband's not out there, my husband
didn't come from the bathroom ten
minutes before I came from work and
"decided" to yell at me, that's all false,
that's maya, that's illusion, got it? He
didn't come out of the bedroom to the
kitchen to yell at me because he decided
to yell at me, that's not what's
happening, what's really happening?
Inside number? Eight, a seed from yelling
at the kids ... last week is opening into a
video in my own mind, and who put it
there?
I did. If you understand you put it there
can number seven get upset? No, and that's
ignorance, that's misunderstanding in the
Mind Only school, got it?
Ignorance, misunderstanding, in the Mind
Only school is: number seven can only
get mad if number seven doesn't
understand number eight, got it? And what's
for $300 ... I was gonna say a thousand but
I'm losing, I don't have that much. Word
you ready? I know you're interested ... what
was the question? That would be
convenient to forget the question ... yeah I
remember the question ... what's going on
when numbers ... what's the root,
or the seed behind number seven not
understanding the husband in number
eight? What's a question
someone's gonna ask you and it's a
difficult ... that's why it's 300 bucks okay.
I'll say it again, Geshe-la says in the
Mind Only school, anger lives in number
seven, upset lives in number seven, off
balance water lives in number seven,
okay, number seven is focused on a seed
opening in number eight as a husband
yelling in the kitchen, okay got it?
Easy question, it's not the three hundred
dollar question, easy question ... is the
husband yelling in the kitchen? No, he's
yelling inside of number eight, okay? Now,
my question to Word for $300 ...
and I remember it ... why does seven think
number eight is outside? I'm sorry inside!
Outside ... outside ...
Nah ...
No, okay first of all you
lost the $300 okay ... I just want to make
that clear first ... and I'll make the
easier question which doesn't deserve
300 dollars.
Why, according to the Mind Only
school, does it feel like what's inside
is outside? Why, in the mind ... according to
the Mind Only school, which is one of the
big questions of the mind only school,
what created misunderstanding, why does
it feel like the husband's over there
when he's really in your own mind?
nice, she should get $300 ... say it again,
you're close
the ... the countless lifetimes of the word
"outside" MNGON BRJOD KYI BAG CHA GS
say MNGON BRJOD KYI BAG CHAGS [abhilāpavāsanā] where did
I teach you that, I never taught you that ...
Oh ... Pure Gold. Yeah okay, there's a
special seed in the mind only school,
that for countless lifetimes you have
talked to your friends about your
husband "over there", and because of that
talking for countless lifetimes you have
a seed in your mind that makes you feel
the husband is over there, when he's
really just in your own mind, got it? And
that's the Mind Only school. Oh Steven
give me something I can answer ...
The second ... the latter ... cool? Got it?
It's a very sophisticated system and
it's pretty cool, it's pretty cool if you
really understand the Mind Only
school it's a pretty cool. Now, why are we
talking about that, we were on the
subject of white pants and spaghetti, we
were on the question ... we are on the
subject of ... why she wears white pants I
have no idea ...
DBYUNG DKA' BA, that oil stain has two
qualities, what are they? (1) it
tends to? Spread. Once you ... once you refuse
to share a cup of coffee you will refuse
to share a meal, you'll refuse to give
people rides in "your" car, you will not
let people stay in "your" house, and then
you will not .... the oil of desire tends ...
not sharing ... tends to spread okay? What
was the second quality? Hard to get out,
hard to get out, you know? Really hard to
get out you know, you should see her
white pants ... they kind of look like
panther pants now, like I wash them and
wash them, but still there's some ...
some stays right, a little bit of stain stays.
I'm thinking to just dye them with black
spots like tiger spots, they'll look
cool right?
... Hard to get out and that's why we went
to Word's text. Why? ... Yeah, when you cut that
tumor out do you cut the brain out? Can
you operate on a human being and take
out consciousness number seven and not
kill the human being? Is it possible to
clean the mind? Is it possible to get
spaghetti olive oil out of white
pants completely or do you have to burn
the pants? That's the question, okay got it?
Okay, that's why we went off on the
Mind Only school. Mister venerable phil
has a question. Loud.
By the way, excuse me, the Mind Only
school says you must? Sorry,
the Abhidharma school says you must?
Burn the pants, you must burn the pants ok? No
other way. There won't be a Michael after
nirvana ok? Disappear.
Venerable Phil.
Yeah, now that's a huge
subject in Tsongkapa, a huge subject, and
I'll say it again, Venerable Phil said,
are ALL kleshas misunderstanding?
Ok? And we're definitely going to talk
about it ok,
it's a big subject this week, it's a huge
subject this week ok.
hmm ...
Now let me say
one more thing about consciousness 7
that Word didn't mention and I barely
remember. Consciousness 7 doesn't just strore
kleshas, it stores other mental functions
other than a few ok, if you say 51 mental
functions or 46, all but a few of them
are in seven ... so if you destroy seven
altogether, do you destroy the whole mind?
That's the question, ok got it?
it's called "klesha consciousness", but
it's not 100% klesha, it's like 80%
other thoughts, that's something they
didn't tell you okay? And there's a
list of them, kun-’gro lnga, yeah okay alright.
Here's ... CHAGS YUL LA SRED ZHEN JE CHER SONG STE
DBRAL BAR DKA,' difficult to get rid
of okay.
Now, that goes to an idim, what's that
mean? What's the idim, what's your idim?
For this one? What's the picture? Yeah, the
guy got spaghetti on his shirt or
something, I think right? What number?
3? Number 3 okay, got it?
So we're gonna meditate about that okay,
do you have to burn the shirt,
can you get the misunderstanding out, can
you cut the brain tumor out without
destroying the mind
okay, got it? 'DOD SRED ZHAGS PAS
'KHOR BA'I BTZON RVAR
BCINGS, I'll say it again and I want a
smart comment on it, by anyone other than
Word. 'DOD SRED I'll say it again ready ...
one two three
'DOD SRED ZHAGS PAS 'KHOR BA'I BTZON RVAR BCINGS, huh?
It's poetry okay, it's poetry
bum bum bum bum ba ba ba
standard Tibetan poetry okay, but the
bum bum bum bum ba ba ba okay,
'DOD SRED ZHAGS PAS 'KHOR BA'I BTZON RVAR BCINGS,
it's always like that ... bum bum bum bum ba ba ba.
Except Milarepa, he's like Dung! dum dum dum dum dung.
Okay, got it? Why am I talking about that?
if you're a translator, you have to smell
poetry.
It means it's coming from another book,
he's quoting somebody okay, he didn't
tell you, but you know from the beat, from
the music of the of the Tibetan okay? You
know he took this from another book, so
who cares? I do ... No, I want to go to that
other book and see what else the guy
said, you seen I mean? And that's why our
translations are so slow, and our lam rim classes okay, wouldn't it be cool to
find that poem and ... and go see the rest
of it, maybe there's something cool there,
you see what I mean? So you should get in this
habit okay, when you see a quotation go
read the book, so I went got it for you
alright, and I'll tell you something
instresting, it's from a tantric poem, I mean a
Diamond Way poem ... about Sukhavati, it's a
paradise of Amitabha or some ... it's a
paradise, it's a poem about Amitabha's
paradise, not bad!
In the middle of kleshas? Okay, what's it
mean? The verse says there's a shark
or it's an arching you are chained in
the prison of suffering because of your
desire pleasure spaghetti stains I mean
he didn't say spaghetti okay but you are
chained in samsara by the oil stain of
Sons of desire okay not sharing what you
have not wanting to share what you have
got it wouldn't it be interesting to see
the other three lines and we can only do
that because of the hard work of John
Brady we should give him a hand he's not
here in here don't clay he's not here
don't clap for him okay okay here's the
whole verse okay and this is why it's
taken eight years to come this far
because I love to go use John Brady's
search tool database he's got like total
with the scans right Cristina it's I
mean Ramachandra stands alone or five
million yeah so you're talking five
million pages okay we can search it in
in three seconds cool Kandra chungee
Tori here's the whole verse okay
from Vajrayana damn diamond way cool and
why did he think of that what was he
doing when he gave the talk okay Kandra
changi Tori sock sock top ching
the sword of anger assassinates your
higher reaper y-yeah it kills your
positive things okay the sort of anger
assassinate your higher rebirth that's
the first line there's a sharper chords
in writing and the handcuffs of desire
spaghetti grease chained you into the
prison of samsara okay Leakey juicy big
yet secure the rushing river of your
karma carries you to the ocean of pain
it carries you down the mountain to the
ocean of pain not getting the ball up
mumble yang and when you get there the
waves of kick garnishee yeah you get old
you constantly having back problems you
know pain chronic pain called life okay
that what do you call tsunami of the
chronic pain called life that's the end
of the pump okay cool
carried down by Karma which is created
by anger and desire got it that's the
whole poem and the whole poem is showing
cause-and-effect it's showing how
clashes create karma which is a big
subject we're gonna do this week okay
without clashes no Karma okay cool come
on without flashes there's no Karma you
cannot collect let's go to the mind only
school who wants to explain that
statement in the mine on mystical
without clashes there's no Karma
yeah unless if you don't think your
husband if you understand your husband's
in your head then you won't yell back
who said that nice got it in the mind on
this school if if mines section seven
apartment seven in the mind understands
apartment eight in the mind then
apartment seven will see the department
aid is just where the husband is yelling
and the husband didn't decide to yell
the husband's coming from me okay got it
then the apartment seven can't be mad at
apartment got it and then apartment
seven will not answer the husband and
won't make new karma got it
question from Miss Kazakh uh yeah but
only thirty ones mmm
I think rightward am i right I think so
we didn't get there yet we'll let you
know next year okay Tim you have
announcements things show that we did
one dollar first Tim you want to lead
them on Donna okay Josh a metal tumbling
Sheen and a camper son Gatien to me
okay Joker nom de Jing Lai chap I sure
AM good man down there yet
they say emissions are touching
siren emission nacho Don Benito cool
thanks for being so patient I know you
have jet lag I know your butts
tired and you're very brave to come here
and sit here for 3-4 hours at a time
you know nobody in the world would do
that except you so you either crazy or
you're special